(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-01T20:26:02.745797",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
みなさん、
Everyone,
こんばんは、はろー！
good evening, hello!
こんばんは！こんばんは！
Good evening! Good evening!
はろー！わーい！はーい！
Hello! Yay! Hi!
と言うことで、えー、まず自己紹介からやっていきましょう。
So, um, let's start with self-introductions.
ホロライブの清楚担当、みんなのアイドル夏色まつりです！
I'm Natsuiro Matsuri, Hololive's seiso representative and everyone's idol!
今日は、えー、MCお願いしまーす、頑張りまーす。
Today, um, I'll be the MC, please wish me luck, I'll do my best.
じゃあ、えーと、今日参加してくださるね、人たち一人ずついきますよ。
Now, um, let's go one by one with the people participating today.
じゃあよっぴーからお願いします！
So Yopi, please go first!
はい！イオフィリアおびさ、どうもでーす。
Yes! Iofitia Obissa, hello.
ホロライブインドネシアからイオフィです！
I'm Iofi from Hololive Indonesia!
今日は、あの、まあ、とぺ、を、ちょっと、えっと、あのことちょっと勉強したいと思います。
Today, um, well, tope, I'd like to study a bit about that, you know.
よろしくお願いします！
Please treat me well!
お願いしまーす！
Please!
じゃあこぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
わかわかわかわかわからないよリバース、Let me be a scientist on your day, えへん。
Waka waka waka I don't understand you, reverse...
わからない連チャンにそう。
a continuous chain of not understanding, yeah.
今日はオノマトペや、えー、勝ちだ。あー、お願いします！
Today onomatopoeia, um, we'll win. Ah, please look forward to it!
うわー！頑張ろう！わーい！
Wow! Let's do our best! Yay!
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Next is Gigi!
こんばんは、ジジです。
Good evening, it's Gigi.
ジモニン、えっと、日本語ちょっと上手くない。
Jimonin, um, my Japanese isn't very good.
え、あの、まだぺ、う、え、ちょっと、え、日本語頑張って！頑張ります！
Um, still pe, u, e, wait, e, Japanese, do your best! I'll do my best!
ありがとう！頑張って！
Thank you! Good luck!
わーい！ジジ頑張って！はい！
Yay! Good luck, Gigi! Yes!
じゃあ、続いてホモJPのねえちゃん。
Next is Homo JP's nee-chan.
いやいやいや、我々はカオスホロライブの白スベルジュです。
No no no, we are chaotic Hololive's Reine Pavolia.
今日は、え、翻訳担当で、え、やりたいと思います。
Today, um, as the translation person, um, I'd like to do it.
よろしくお願いします！
Please treat me well!
お願いしまーす！
Please!
のあ、よろしくお願いします！
Noah, please!
じゃあ最後がローラ！
And finally, Raora!
こんにちはー！
Hello!
ララパンテラです！
It's Raora Panthera!
今日は、えっと、絵を描いたり日本語で話したり頑張りまーす！
Today, um, I'll do my best drawing pictures and speaking Japanese!
はい、お願いします！
Yes, please!
お上手ー！お願いします！
Very good! Please!
ということでね、本日はですね、皆さんにオノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます。
So today, everyone will be answering an onomatopoeia quiz.
あの、ちょっとね、日本独特の表現とかもたくさんあるんですが、頑張って答えてね。
Um, there are many unique Japanese expressions, but do your best to answer.
はい、はい。あの、ぜひ日本の、
Yes, yes. Um, please use Japanese...
カルチャーは一杯使って頂きたいなと思います。はい、ということで、はい！
culture a lot. Yes, so, yes!
早速第1問いきましょう！
Let's get right into Question 1!
おーい！
Ooh!
はい、クエスチョンワン！
Yes, Question 1!
このオノマトペは何を表しているでしょうか？え、コケッコッコー！
What does this onomatopoeia represent? Um, Cock-a-doodle-doo!
あれ？なんかペンがおかしいんです、私。なんで？
Huh? My pen is acting weird. Why?
え？おかしい？
Eh? Weird?
コケコッコー！けっこうけっこうこっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo! Cluck-cluck-cluck-cluck!
ペンがおかしい。あれ、なんで？こんな…かけるかな？
The pen is weird. Huh, why? Can I... draw this?
ちょっと待ってください。アプリ再起動します。
Please wait a moment. I'll restart the app.
Should we draw?
I drew 'cause I don't know what it is in Japanese.
It's alright.
I don't know the word.
あ、待ってください。はい。かけるかな？あ、かけます。あ、よかった。
Ah, please wait. Yes. Can I draw? Ah, I can. Ah, great.
おわった。コケコッコー。声に出したらわかるか。
Done. Cock-a-doodle-doo. If I make a sound, you'll get it.
コケコッコー！遠い…。大丈夫か？コケコッコーですよ。
Cock-a-doodle-doo! Far away… Is it okay? It's cock-a-doodle-doo.
オッケー、じゃあ、一人ずつ聞いていきましょう。
Okay, then let's go and listen one by one.
じゃあよぴぴ、なんだと思いますか？
So Yopipi, what do you think it is?
あ、チキンです！あ、チキン。鶏ね。
Ah, it's chicken! Ah, chicken. A chicken.
Ah, before I was thinking about frog, but I think cock-a-doodle-doo, it sounds like Indonesian, kukuruyuk! So it's chicken.
なんか、もともとカエルだと思ってたんだけど、インドネシアのオノマトペでも、オノマトペ…。鶏の鳴き声に似てるので。
I originally thought it was a frog, but Indonesian onomatopoeia sounds like a chicken's cry, so...
似てるね。チキン。なるほどね。
It does. Chicken. I see.
じゃあ、じじ。けっけっコケコッコー！英語は…コッカードゥードゥードゥー！
Then Gigi. K-k-cock-a-doodle-doo! English is... Cock-a-doodle-doo!
あ、僕も鶏。チキン、だと思います。
Ah, I also think it's chicken. Chicken.
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming like 'cuckoo!' Like, 'I'm here!' and... Koko? Koko? I'm here! And maybe she knows food in his mouth because maybe it's small, you know? I don't know.
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming like 'cuckoo!' Like, 'I'm here!' and... Koko? Koko? I'm here! And maybe it has food in its mouth.
さけぶとり。さけぶとりね。鶏は鶏でもさけぶとりだから。なんか、お腹空いてるさけぶとりね。
A screaming bird. A screaming bird. A screaming bird instead of a regular chicken. A hungry screaming bird.
じゃあ、正解いきましょう。正解は、チキン、鶏でしたー！
Okay, let's go with the correct answer. The correct answer was chicken!
さけぶとりだもんね。鶏、鶏は鶏なんだけど、同じ同じだからね。素晴らしい！
It's a screaming bird, right? Chicken is still a chicken, but they're the same. Wonderful!
続いて第2問！こちらも動物の鳴き声でございます。
Next is Question 2! This is also an animal's cry.
じゃあ第2問、こちらケロケロ。
Then Question 2, this one: ribbit ribbit.
Easy easy! Easy easy!
ケロケロ…え？虫…？え…？すごい…何々何々？
Kerokero... Eh? An insect...? Eh...? Amazing... What, what, what?
え、マイペン。オッケー、ワッツ。
Eh, my pen. Okay, what's...
Thank you.
ベータちゃんのはなに？ホールドン、アイフォゴットワットイットルックライク！
What is Beta-chan's? Hold on, I forgot what it looked like!
ワットアーユードライイング？ホワイイズシードローイングハーセルフ？アイフォゴットワットイットルックライク！
What are you drawing? Why is she drawing herself? I forgot what it looked like!
ベェが描く。キメラ、だよ。
Bae draws. It's a chimera, you know.
お前ら？ひまわり、の
You guys? Sunflower, no-
ひまわりのやめて。
Stop it, Sunflower.
おいっちゃ、ちょっと1人ずつまた聞いていきますか。
Hey guys, shall we go around and listen to each of you?
かわいい、みんな。
Everyone is so cute.
え、じゃあ、よぴぴ。
Um, well then, Yopipi.
はい。
Yes!
蛙です。
It's a frog.
ああ、蛙。
Ah, a frog.
ケロ、ケロ、ケロ、ケロ。
Kero, kero, kero, kero.
なるほど。それは、はい。
I see. That is, yes.
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ、続いてこぶちゃん。
Next, Kobu-chan.
私も蛙、蛙？蛙蛙？
Me too, a frog, frog? Frog frog?
蛙、蛙？
Frog, frog?
蛙、はい。ケロ、ケロ、ケロ、ケロ。
Frog, yes. Kero, kero, kero, kero.
すごい。
Amazing.
おお。
Ooh.
祭りも鳴けないよ、蛙。
You can't even croak in a festival, frog.
それでは続いてじじ。
Next up is Gigi.
はい。
Yes!
ケロ、ケロ、ケロピー、ケロ、ケロ、ケロピー。
Kero, kero, keropy, kero, kero, keropy.
なるほど。
I see.
じゃあ、べーちゃん。
Next, Bae-chan.
あ、蛙です。
Ah, it's a frog.
蛙かな？蛙か？蛙か？蛙？
Is it a frog? A frog? A frog? A frog?
蛙、蛙。
Frog, frog.
一瞬ずつね、一瞬で耳がやられたんだけど。
One by one... my ears got wrecked in an instant.
蛙見たことないんで。
Because I've never seen a frog.
はい、蛙。
Yes, a frog.
蛙が白黒。
The frog is black and white.
その隣のラオラ、めっちゃ上手い。
Laora next to her is so good.
かわいい。かわいい。
So cute. So cute.
蛙ですね？
It's a frog, right?
蛙です。
It's a frog.
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ、ケロケロ正解は蛙でございまーす！
Well then, "kero kero", the correct answer is a frog!
正解！
Correct!
イージー、イージー、イージー。
Easy, easy, easy.
できなかったのだれ？
Who couldn't do it?
日本語上手。
Your Japanese is good.
日本語上手よ。
じゃあ、続いていきますよ。続いては、
Now, let's keep going. Next is...
え、こちら、馬の鳴き声は日本だと何と言うでしょ？
Um, what do people in Japan say a horse's neigh sounds like?
なんて聞こえるかな？なんて聞こえるかな？
What does it sound like? What does it sound like?
ハリキッテイコウ！
Let's do our best!
耳、イメージ、イメージして。
Listen closely, use your imagination.
じじ、フィーリングで心からのやつ！
Gigi, go with your feeling from the heart!
君ならできる！1人ずつ泣いてもらうからね。
You can do it! I'm going to make each of you cry one by one.
じじから、じじの馬の鳴き声おお願いしまーす！
Starting with Gigi, please give us your horse neigh, Gigi!
どうぞ！ハリキッテイコウです！
Go ahead! "Let's do our best!"
じゃあ、よぴぴからよぴぴの馬の鳴き声おお願いしまーす！
Now, from Yopipi, please give us your horse neigh, Yopipi!
どうぞ！ハリキッテイコウ！です！
Go ahead! "Let's do our best!"
え？馬ってこれしかないですよ！馬薄すぎる！
Eh? Is that all a horse sounds like? That's way too faint for a horse!
じゃあ、続いて、え、こぶちゃん。
Well then, next, um, Kobu-chan.
えー、ひひ、ひひ。
Uh, hihi, hihi.
ひひ、あ、ひひ。
Hihi, ah, hihi.
I feel like that's a different sound, あれ、なんか別のあれじゃない？
I feel like that's a different sound, wait, isn't that something else?
は？
Huh?
ひひ、ひひ、別じゃ？ひひ、ひひ。
Hihi, hihi, isn't that different? Hihi, hihi.
じゃあ、続いてじじ。
Next up is Gigi.
じゃあ、続いてべーちゃん。
Next, Bae-chan.
うま！うま！めっちゃ日本語喋るやん。
Uma! Uma! You speak Japanese so well.
じゃあ、続いて、え、ラオラ。
Next, um, Laora.
オッケー、えー、え、maybe something like turning into horse, You're a cat, what does a horse sound like?
Okay, um, maybe something like turning into a horse, you're a cat, what does a horse sound like?
世界は、馬の鳴き声って何？
What does the world say a horse's neigh sounds like?
ヒヒーンでした。
It was "hihiin".
ヒヒ？
Hihi?
ヒヒーンが？ヒヒーン。
"Hihiin"? Hihiin.
イエス、イエス、イエス。ヒヒーン。
Yes, yes, yes. Hihiin.
ヒヒーンだったらラオラじゃないの？
If it's hihiin, isn't that Laora?
でもラオラはリアルすぎかな？リアルすぎ？ヒヒーンがヒヒーン。
But is Laora too realistic? Too realistic? Hihiin is hihiin.
あ、there's an N at the end.
Ah, there's an N at the end.
ヒヒーン。そう、ヒヒーン。Why do horses make that sound?
Hihiin. Yes, hihiin. Why do horses make that sound?
Sound like Michael Jackson.
ハリキッテいこう！
Let's get fired up!
私カウント？
My count?
ヒヒーンだよヒヒーン！
It's "hihiin"!
のヒヒーン？
"No hihiin"?
のヒヒーン、の、ヒヒーンの、フの？
"No hihiin", "no", "hihiin no", "fu no"?
のカウント？
"No count"?
のカウント、のカウント、ソーリー
"No count", "no count", sorry!
ヒヒーンヒヒーン可愛いけどね
"Hihiin hihiin", it's cute though.
残念ながら不正解でございます。あらま。
Unfortunately, that is incorrect. Oh well.
では続いて、今から、インド言葉の意味をね当ててください。じゃあ行きます。
Now next, please guess the meaning of Indonesian words. Here we go.
ぺこぺこだー！
"Peko peko da!"
の意味は？
What does it mean?
え、ぺこぺこ、ぺこぺこ、ハングリー
Um, peko peko, peko peko, hungry.
お、みんな、スラスラと書いてくれている。
Oh, everyone is writing smoothly.
ぺこぺこ、ぺこぺこ、ぺこぺこだー！
Peko peko, peko peko, peko peko da!
ぺこぺこだー、うん。
Peko peko da, yeah.
オッケーかな？可愛いイラストがかかれている。
Is that okay? There are cute illustrations drawn.
じゃあ聞いていきますか。よぴぴ。
Shall we hear them then? Yopipi, go ahead.
ハングリーです！
Hungry!
食べたいです、プリング、食べたいです！
I want to eat, spring, I want to eat!
ぺこぺこです。じゃあこぶちゃん。
It's peko peko. Next, Kobu-chan.
はい！ぺこぺこ、インドネシア語の意味はラッパーです。
Yes! Peko peko, in Indonesian, it means "laper".
ラッパーとはどういう意味ですか？
What does "laper" mean?
よぴ？
Yopimi?
ラッパーはハングリー！
Laper is hungry!
あ、ハングリー！あー！
Ah, hungry! Ah!
ハングリー、ハングリー！
Hungry, hungry!
ハングリーね、オッケー。
Hungry, okay.
じゃあじじ！じじ顔だけ書いてない！
Next, Jiji! Jiji hasn't drawn anything except the face!
お腹空きすぎた、ぺこぺこだ！
I'm too hungry, peko peko da!
お腹空きすぎた！ぺこぺこだー！じじ可愛い。
Too hungry! Peko peko da! Jiji is cute.
じゃあ続いてべーちゃん。
Next, Be-chan.
はい、ハングリーです。あれ、お腹...
Yes, I'm hungry. Wait, my stomach...
腹ぺこ、オッケー。
Harapeko, okay.
じゃあローラ、あ、ベリーハングリー！
Next, Laura. Ah, very hungry!
あ、じゃあ全員同じだね。全員ハングリー。
Ah, so everyone is the same. Everyone's hungry.
可愛い。ハングリー、ハングリー。
Cute. Hungry, hungry.
ええ、ということで
Um, with that being said,
全員正解！
everyone is correct!
じじも、べーちゃんもハングリーね。じゅーじゅー。
Jiji and Be-chan are hungry too. Juu juu.
はい、じゃあ続いてもう、あててください。意味をあててくださいね。
Yes, then next, please guess another one. Please guess the meaning.
あ、ネクストワンはオースゲストミーニング
Ah, the next one is also guess the meaning.
じゃあ行きます。オッケー？
Here we go. Ready?
チンしてね！の意味は？
What does "chin shite ne!" mean?
あ！チン、チンしてね！チンしてね！
Ah! Chin, chin shite ne! Chin shite ne!
チンしてね、チンしてね。
Chin shite ne, chin shite ne.
プリーズ、なんだろう？え？チンしてね。
Please, I wonder what it is? Eh? Chin shite ne.
チン、チンしてね。可愛い、可愛い、可愛い。
Chin, chin shite ne. Cute, cute, cute.
え、チン、チンしてね。チンしてね。
Um, chin, chin shite ne. Chin shite ne.
チン、チンしてね。
Chin, chin shite ne.
分かるかな？
Do you know?
声に出したら分かるかもよ。
You might understand if you say it out loud.
チン、チン。ピープル、プリーズ？違うな。
Chin, chin. People, please? No, that's not it.
ここだな、ちょっと下にね、書いて。
Right here, write it a bit lower.
はい、じゃあ聞きますか。え、よぴぴどうでしょう？
Yes, shall we ask? Um, Yopipi, how about you?
はい、最初はおしゃれなんか、ドアのベルだったんだけど、あれピンポンだからチンしたらあのマイクロウェーブ？
Yes, at first it was like a door bell, but since that's ping-pong, if you chin it, that's microwave?
あ、マイクロウェーブ！あの温める？
Ah, microwave! The thing that warms things up?
温まったらチンってなるじゃん。
When it warms up, it goes "chin", right?
うん、うん、なるほど。おっけー。
Yeah, yeah, I see. Okay.
じゃあこぶちゃんは、あれ？これ、こぶちゃん、こぶちゃん、これは
Then Kobu-chan, huh? This, Kobu-chan, Kobu-chan, this is
なんか、チンはちょっと、やばい、やばい、やばい、やばい。
like, chin is a bit... oh no, oh no, oh no, oh no.
危険、こぶちゃん、そんな見たい、そんなもの見たい。
Dangerous, Kobu-chan, I want to see that, I want to see that kind of thing.
あ、その、チンは、チン、あ、ら、そう、チンしてね。チン、プリーズ。チン、プリーズ、プリーズ...
Ah, that "chin" is... chin, ah, right, "chin shite ne". Chin please. Chin please, please...
え、わかんない。わかんない。
Eh, I don't know. I don't know.
じゃあ次、次行きますか。ジジジジジジ
Shall we go to the next one? Ji-ji-ji-ji...
え、わかんない。
Eh, I don't know.
ち、やばい？
Chin yobai?!
ち、やばくない！？やばい！ち、やばい！
Chin yabai! That's so yabai! Chin yabai!
の、やばい。やばくない！もう。
No, yabai. It's not yabai! Jeez.
じゃ、ぺいちゃん、ぺいちゃんお願いします。
Now, Pei-chan, Pei-chan, please.
はい。ペニーのチンですね。
Yes. Penny's "chin", right?
で、あたためてっていうことです。Please go warm it up in the microwave.
And it means "warm it up". Please go warm it up in the microwave.
ああ、はいはいはい。
Ah, yes, yes, yes.
じゃあ最後、ラオラ。えー、わかんない。わかんない。
Then last, Raora. Uhh, I don't know. I don't know.
わかんない。
I don't know.
maybe...
maybe when when the glass, when it touch the glass
Maybe when the glass, when it touches the glass...
ああ、ガラス？
Ah, glass?
ガラス、ね。シーンって言うか。
Glass, right? Like "shing".
確かに。はいはいはい。な、やばい？
True. Yes, yes, yes. Na, yabai?
の、のやばいね。ノットやばい。
No, yabai. Not yabai.
もうわかんないよ。わかんない。
I just don't know. I don't know.
じゃあ、こちらはですね、正解は「マイクロウェーブ」
Well, as for this one, the correct answer is "microwave".
チン！ごはんを温めてくださいっていう。
Chin! Please warm up your rice.
あー、なるほど。レンジでチンしてね！って言うもんね。
Ah, I see. "Chin it in the microwave!" is what people say.
ええと、チンしてね！ああ、なるほど。例えば、ご飯をこう置いといて、えー、あとに帰ってきた人、ご飯が冷めかかってるからチンしてね！ってメモを残したりしますね。
Uh, "Chin it!" Ah, I see. For example, if you leave rice out, and someone comes back later, since the rice is getting cold, you leave a memo saying "Chin it!"
なるほど、なるほど！
I see, I see!
こぼこぼちんしてね、ちん、ちんしてね。Please warm it up for me.
Kobo kobo chin, chin, chin. Please warm it up for me.
あー、オッケー。そう。if you wanna, if you wanna say pee, please...
Ah, okay. So, if you wanna say pee, please...
How do you say that? I might need that one.
じょじょピー！ノッピ！
Jojo pee! Not pee!
ノッピ！あ、じゃあピーはどう言ったらいいの？
No pee! Ah, then how do you say pee?
オノマトペや。ピープリーズ！ピープリーズ！
Onomatopoeia. Pee please! Pee please!
ピー！おしっこ？おしっこ！
Pee! Pee? Pee!
あじゃあ、シーとかです。シー、シャーーとか。
Ah, then, "shh" or something. "Shh", "shaa" or something.
シャーー、シャープリーズ！シャーシーほど。
Shaa, shaa please! Shaa-shh or something.
シャーー、おしっこ！シャー、の、の、の！
Shaa, pee! Shaa, no, no, no!
ノー、ダメね！ダメダメよ！
No, don't do that! Don't do that!
すみません、シャー。ノー！ダメ、ダメ！おしっこ！ありがとございます！わかりました！やばい！
Excuse me, shaa. No! Don't, don't! Pee! Thank you very much! I understand! Yabai!
え、じゃあ、ネクスト行きましょう。こちらでございます。えー、静まり返ったとき、めっちゃ静かなとき使うオノマトペは何でしょうか。
Uh, well, let's go to the next. Here it is. Uh, what is the onomatopoeia used when it gets dead silent, when it's super quiet?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really quiet?
あー、maybe I remember. え？あ、なんだっけ。静かなとき。
Ah, maybe I remember. Eh? Ah, what was it? When it's quiet.
What that mean? What? Really really quiet, what that mean? 静かなときも音がある？
What that mean? What? Really, really quiet, what that mean? Even when it's quiet, there's a sound?
Like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
漫画読んだらわかるかもね。漫画に書いてあることもあるかも。ジャパニーズ漫画。
You might know if you read manga. It might be written in manga. Japanese manga.
Might be in manga that you've read before... What is it? Like that? Is that how you spell it?
まあいいでしょう。じゃあ聞いてきますね、よぴぴから。
Well, that's fine. Then let's ask Yopipi.
アイ、シーン。はい、シーンぷり、多分ね。こうやってシーン、あー、はいはいはい。
I, shh. Yes, "shh" probably. Like "shh", ah, yes, yes, yes.
え、続いてこぼちゃん。シーン。シーン、はいはいはい。
Next, Kobo-chan. "Shh." "Shh," yes, yes, yes.
じゃ、ジジ。え、シャー！シャー！シャー！シャー！
Then, Jiji. Eh, "shaa"! "Shaa"! "Shaa"! "Shaa"!
まままま、isn't that the pee? No!
Wait, wait, wait, isn't that the pee? No!
Well, won't it get quiet after you pee?
Oh.
じゃあ続いて、ベチャ。
That leads to... Beh-chan?
いや、忘れた。なんか、すん？あー、すん？
Wait, um, is it sum?
違う。すんは ちょっと違うか。
No, sum is a bit different.
しになったか。 いや、どっちかと思ってたんだよね。なるほどなるほど。
Shi? I thought it was either or, you know?
じゃあ、だーらだーら。
Let's see.
うーん。
Hmm.
お、ジジ？うん。
Oh, Giga?
あ、あ、いや、I think it's shin!
Yeah, I think it's shin!
Like, I remember when I read some mangas, but I might be wrong. Maybe it's shin.
Okay.
マンガに、オッケー、got it, got it. Okay?
Manga, okay, got it, got it. Okay?
じゃあ、正解に行きましょう。
Let's go with the correct answer.
正解は...
The correct answer is...
Shin！
Shin!
やったー！わあ、どら、どら、どら！
Woohoo! Wow, Dora! Dora! Dora!
が正解だぜ！
That's correct!
やった！Yea, you're so close, GIGI, you're so close!
Yay! You're so close, Gigi!
You're so close!
GIGIのは、惜しい。Shin! Shin!
Gigi was close, shin! Shin!
そう、し...
So...
Nが必要ですね、こぼちゃん。しーん。
"N" is needed, Kobachan. Shi-n.
あ、そうですね。しーん！
Ah, that's right. Shi-n!
Very close!
Very close! まあまあまあ、close enough!
Close enough.
まあまあまあ。
Fair enough, fair enough.
ジジは絶対違うからね。
Gigi is definitely different, though.
シャワー？ え？ちょっと、違うですか？シャワーって。
Shower? Wait, is it shower?
そう、さっきのPの音... P soundの。
Right, the previous P sound...
いや、でも、一応 なんか理屈的にも間違ってないと思うすけどね。え？
Yeah, but logically speaking, I think it's not wrong either, you know?
シャ...
Sha...
GIGIがさ、だっておしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん。
Like, after you pee, it gets quiet, right?
あ、そうそうそう。だから、シャ...
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's why sha...
シャ...
Sha...
シャ... ちょっと違うか。
A bit different?
I was explaining your logic.
Ah, okay, thank you. So you're defending me?
Yeah, I was defending you.
はい。
Right.
Got you, got you.
続いて行きましょう。続いて。
Let's move on. Next...
えー、とっても冷たい飲み物を表すオノトピアは何でしょうか？
What is the onomatopoeia for an extremely cold drink?
What's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
のみもの？そう、drink?
Drink? Nomimono?
ええ、あの、あれとあれ、だけど。何々に冷えたって言いますね。
Wait, it's something like that, but it's like "cooled".
あれでしょ。うん。
That must be it.
Cold drink?
I only have one word in my head again.
Cold drink? Cold drink?
これもね、マンガに出てくるかもね。
This might also appear in manga, maybe?
It'll be manga.
It could be manga.
わかんない！
I don't know!
Image? Ice?
Ice?
What sound am I making?
What do you have? Just do it, just do it!
What are you hiding? Just do it, just do it!
I'm scared!
No!
It's okay!
GIGIが なんかやばそうだ。GIGI、体調、大丈夫？
Gigi looks like she's in trouble. Is she okay?
大丈夫？GIGI大丈夫。大丈夫、大丈夫、大丈夫。
Are you okay? Gigi is okay. It's okay.
大丈夫。はいはいはい。
It's okay.
でも、あれかな。ビールとかに結構言うかな？
Well, maybe it's used for beer and stuff, I guess?
ビールか。
Beer?
These would be...
Okay.
じゃあ行きますか。
Let's go.
え、じゃあYOPPI。
Yopi?
はい。確か、キンキナンなんとかのです。
I think it's kin-kin-n... something like that.
はい。
Yes!
えっと、なんか、あ、この前スタジオで誰かさんの、ホロメンか誰かさんが、あのマネージャーにキンキンの飲み物欲しいですって言われたの。おお、なるほど！
And, um, this one time in the studio, someone... Hololive, someone said to the manager, "I want a kin-kin drink," and I heard that.
なるほど！
I see.
そうそうそうそう。去年の夏ぐらいで、うん、誰かさん ちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオでなんか聞いたことがあります。
That's right, around last summer... I kind of forgot, but I heard it in the studio.
あ、キンキンね。
Ah, kin-kin, right?
Okay.
じゃあ、KOBO。
Kobo?
Ah, so I felt like when you after you drink cold, a really cold drink, you're a... after that your head will hurt and then you'll say "a-ta-ta".
ああ！あたたた！
Ah! A-ta-ta!
なんか、冷たい飲み物飲んだ後さ、頭痛くなるんじゃないですか。その時に、あたたたた！
Like, after you drink something cold, your head starts to hurt, doesn't it? At that time, "a-ta-ta-ta!".
なるほどね。
I see, I see.
はい。
Right.
だからこそ、あたたたた！ってことね。たしかに。
That's why "a-ta-ta-ta!" I get it.
OK, OK。
Okay, okay.
あー。
Ah.
はいはい。じゃあ続いて、GIGI。
Okay, okay. Then next, Gigi.
サムい！
Samui!
サムいよね？サムい。
Samui, right? Samui.
サムい。
Samui.
Yes.
サムい？
Samui?
サムい、うまい！サムい、うまい！
Samui, umai! Samui, umai!
可愛い。
Cute.
オッケー？サムい。
Okay? Samui.
サムい飲み物、オッケー？
Samui drink, okay?
はい。
Okay!
可愛い！
Cute!
じゃあ続いてべーちゃん。
Okay, next is Bechan.
なんかキーから始まった気がした。あ、忘れた。
I feel like it started with "Ki", wait, I forgot.
キーから始まるんなら、き、な、なんちゃらって感じキー。き、き、ん。
It starts with "Ki"... "Ki-", something like that. "Ki"... "Ki", "Ki".
き、きんで。
"Kin"?
あ、き、き。
Ah, "Ki". "Ki".
オッケーオッケーオッケーオッケー。キー。
Okay, okay, okay, okay. "Ki".
じゃあローラ。
Then, Laura.
あー、えーと、カンパイ！
"It's a Kanpai!"
あ、カンパイ！やったー、カンパイ！
Kanpai! Cheers! Cheers!
やった！レッツゴー！
Let's go! Let's go!
やった！レッツゴー、オッケー！
Let's go, okay!
カンパイ！
Kanpai!
じゃあ正解いきましょう。
Okay, let's go with the correct answer.
正解は、きん、きんに冷えた飲み物でございますので、きんきんです！
The correct answer is: a drink that is chilled "Kin-kin"!
きんきんです！妖怪すごい！
"Kinkin"! So cool!
やった！ありがとうございます、だりかさんの、おろべんの。
Yay, thank you Darika-san.
ねえ、だりかさんありがとうございます。新しい、きんか？はい。きんきん。
Darika-san, thank you. New "Kinka"?
きんきん、きんきんに冷えてやがるっていうセリフが
"Kinkin", "Kinkin" chilled to the bone—
アニメにもありますね。
That's in an anime too, right?
ほほほ。
Ho ho ho.
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ続いては、ええと、いきますか。
Then next, shall we?
続いてこちら。
Next is this one.
よいしょ。
Hold on.
キラキラ、星がキラキラしてるみたいな、キラキラの
"Kirakira", like the stars are twinkling—
もっと強い表現。
An even stronger expression.
もっとキラキラ！
"Motto kirakira"!
もっと、まぶしい？ん？
"Motto mabushii"? Huh?
どう表現するでしょうか。
How would you express it?
How would you describe something that you know you have kirakira to describe something that's sparkling, something that's even more bright and shiny, more than kirakira?
How would you describe something that has "kirakira", something that's even brighter and shinier, more than "kirakira"?
There's a couple of different variations.
This has a couple of different variations.
あれ、なんだかあの、ほにゃららの、えっと、ポケモンを思い出しゃって
What was it... some kind of...
ポケモン！
Pokemon!
So so like kirakira, but upgrade- more stronger.
So, like, "kirakira" but stronger?
Yeah, like more- with more punch, level up kirakira.
Yeah, like with more punch, level up "kirakira".
Level up kirakira, powerful kirakira.
わかるかな。
Can you guess?
可愛い。
How cute.
書いてくれてる、お祭りを。
They are writing it down at the festival.
可愛い。
So cute.
I'm bribing the judge.
What?
Why?
I don't know the word.
なんかMCさんにわいろ送ってます。
I'm bribing MC-san.
お、もう一回。
One more?
何々？
What, what?
あの、知らないので、あの、MCにわいろ送ってます。
Since I don't know, I'm bribing MC-san.
じゃあヒントね、ヒント。
Then, hint, hint.
ヒントは、え、ホロライブメンバーの曲の歌詞に入ってますね。
Hint is, it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song.
もっと言うと、ホロライブのメンバーのソング
More precisely, it's in a Hololive member's song...
ねねちの、あの曲、「ねねちのソング」
Nenene's song, "Nenene Song"
に入ってる。
is included.
あとはキラキラの進化。
Also, "Kirakira's" evolution?
キラキラパワーアップさせた感じかな？
"Kirakira power up" kind of feeling?
それがヒント。
That's a hint.
どうでしょうか。
How's that?
わかるかな。
Do you know?
オッケー、わいろオッケー？
Okay, bribe okay?
わいろは……
Bribe is...
え、これわいろくれたの誰？誰がくれたの？
Who gave the bribe?
じじ？　ローラ？じじかな。じじ？
Jiji? Or Laura? Jiji, right?
じじ？じじじじじじじ。
Jiji? Jiji? Jiji?
じじじゃあ、わいろとして、あの、Very cute boy's please、祭りお姉ちゃんオッケー？
Jiji, as a bribe, "Very cute boy's please, festival Onee-chan, okay?"
たぶん、あの、あの映画のわいろの話を。
She talked about that, that, that movie with bribes.
あ、そういう？
Ah, is that so?
でも言ってた、少し。え、きらきら、きらきら、え、え、
She said, "Kirakira, kirakira..."
まっとうじ、お姉さん！きらきら！
"Mattouji Onee-san, kirakira!"
大好き！
I love it.
きもちわる！やば！
Gross! Gross! Oh no!
あ、じじ、あの、your nameワード、ヒント、your nameワード？
Ah, Jiji, "your name" password, hint, "your name" password?
Your name is a hint? It is.
オッケー？
Okay?
あ、あ、あれね！うん。
Ah, ah, that's it!
で、え、まあ、ねねっちの曲にも入ってるよと。
And, well, Nenene's song also has it, you know.
オッケー。
Okay.
いけるかな？
Are we ready?
じゃあ聞いてこ。じゃあ、ヨピピーから。
Then let's listen. Starting with Yopi-p.
はい。えーと、キラーん彼女、キラキラとか、そういうの？
Yes. Um, like "kiran", "kira-kira", stuff like that?
かなと思って、でも今思ってたらあれだなと思ってて。
I thought, but thinking about it now, I realized something.
お！書けますか？
Oh! Can you write it?
いらん。
Never mind.
あ、いや、大丈夫です！
Ah, no, it's fine!
でもなんか、そう、なんかそのキラキラもっと強いのが、なんかいつもの対応対応なんか、あ、対応ピピピってなっちゃうじゃないですか。
But you know, like, the stronger version of "kira-kira", usually for responses... like it becomes "P-P-P", right?
対応によく使われるものかな。なるほど。
It's something often used for responses, I guess. I see.
じゃあ、コボちゃん。
Next, Kobo-chan.
I heard someone saying...
ポケモン、あははは。
Pokémon... hahaha.
So I think like... Pika Pika!
ピカピカ！
Pika Pika!
めちゃ強いじゃん！ピカピカ、めっちゃ強い。
That's super strong! Pika Pika is super strong.
確かに強い。確かに強いピカピカは。
True, it's strong. Pika Pika is definitely strong.
ストロング、ストロングピカピカ。
Strong, strong Pika Pika.
じゃあ、続いてじじ。
Next, Gigi.
じじは、きらきら、きらきら。
Gigi's is "kira-kira, kira-kira".
ぎらぎら、ぎらぎら。
"gira-gira, gira-gira".
はあはあはあ、ぎらぎら、オッケー？
Aha, "gira-gira", okay?
じゃあ、ベネちゃんいきましょう。
Next, let's go with Vene-chan.
あ、僕もピカピカだと思ってた。ピカピカね。
Ah, I also thought it was Pika Pika. Pika Pika, right?
オッケー。
Okay.
え、じゃあ、ラオラ？あ、先日見、あ、聞いたわ、ポケモン。
Um, then Raora? Ah, I heard about Pokémon recently.
ポケモンピカピカって言ってさ。ピカピカ、ピカピカ。ポケモンヒットだからね。
Talking about Pokémon Pika Pika. Pika Pika, Pika Pika. Because Pokémon is a hit.
なるほどね、ポケモンヒント。オッケー。
I see, Pokémon hint. Okay.
じゃあ、正解いきましょう。
Now, let's go with the correct answer.
正解は、ぎらぎらでじじ正解！
The correct answer is "gira-gira", and Gigi got it right!
やったー！やったやった！ぎらぎら。
Yay! We did it! "gira-gira".
天才じゃん！天才天才天才！
You're a genius! Genius, genius, genius!
買収されたわ。買収されたわ、これ。えー、ぎらぎら。
I've been bought out. I was bought out for this. Eh, "gira-gira".
ピカピカちょっと惜しくて、それがね、ビカビカとかだったら正解。
Pika Pika was a bit close, if it was "vika-vika" or something, that'd be correct.
ああ、ビビカ、もっと眩しいね。
Ah, "bibika", even more dazzling.
あ、ビカビカの方が強いんだ。そう、ピカピカはまあ、キラキラと同じくらいだから。
Ah, "bika-bika" is stronger. Yeah, Pika Pika is about the same as Kira Kira.
なるほど。ちょっと弱いかな。ビカビカ、ぎらぎら。
I see. A bit weaker, huh? Bika-bika, gira-gira.
ピカピカはまあ、キラキラと同じくらい。
Pika Pika is on the same level as Kira Kira.
でもさ、いつも聞いてのが、なんかギラギラ太陽なんとかって、聞いてる気がする。
But you know, I always hear stuff like "gira-gira sun" or something.
ネネちのね、あのギラファもね、ギラファーム、ギラファームミーティングギラファとかもね。
Nenechi's, um, Giraffa too, "Girafarm Meeting Giraffa" and stuff.
本当同じ感じで、明るい、まぶしい、みたいな。
It's the same kind of bright, dazzling feeling.
I see, I see. When you know driving works... driving works, I mean I could drive.
続いていきましょう。続いて同じ感じでございますけども、心臓のこの音、ドキドキをもっと強く表現すると。
Let's continue. Next, in a similar fashion, if you express the sound of a heartbeat, "dokidoki", even stronger.
Stronger dokidoki?
これもね、なんか何パターンかあるから、あってたら大丈夫。あるんだろな。
There are a few patterns for this too, so if it matches, it's fine. There should be.
どちらでもいいって感じですか、そしたら。
So either is fine, basically?
まあ、2つ3つくらい表現はあるかな。
Well, there are maybe two or three expressions.
ドキドキね。
Dokidoki, right.
ドキドキ、強く、強く。
Dokidoki, strongly, strongly.
ちなみに弱くすると、まあ、弱くすると、
By the way, if you make it weaker, well, if you make it weaker,
とくん、とくんとかですね。
it's like "tokun, tokun".
Another like, similar level is tokun tokun, so that's a hint. So you want something stronger than tokun tokun.
これもちょっとなんか可愛い声で、祭り先輩、祭りお姉さんって言ったらもっとヒントくれます？
Also, with a cute voice, if you say Matsuri-senpai, Matsuri-oneesan, will you give us more hints?
ヒント！ヒント！ちょっとヒントくれます？
Hint! Hint! Can you give us a hint?
かわいい祭りお姉さんって言ったらヒントくれます？
If I call you cute Matsuri-oneesan, will you give us a hint?
ああ、オッケー、オッケー。いいよ、どうぞ。
Ah, okay, okay. Sure, go ahead.
え、え、いいですか？
Eh, eh, is that okay?
いいよ。
Sure.
うん、いいですか？
Um, is it okay?
うん。
Yeah.
祭りおね
Matsuri-one-
ねえちゃん、ちょっとあのヒントをお願いしまーす！
Nee-chan, could you give us a hint, please?
え、ないよ？
Huh, there isn't one?
えー！ひとつだけでいいからおねえちゃん！
What?! Just one hint is fine, Onee-chan!
オーマイガー！
Oh my god!
めっちゃこれヒントだけど、
Well, here's a huge hint:
うーん、まあ、強調するのに日本では結構ちっちゃい「つ」を入れたりとか…
Um, well, to emphasize it, in Japanese we often use a small 'tsu'...
あー！あと、ドキドキです！
Ah! Also, 'dokidoki'!
そうですね。あと、言葉を変えるんだったら、あの、なんだろ、なんだろな、っきな、おっきなおとっぽいというか…まあ、どうもね、おっきそうだけどね。
That's right. And if you change the words, um, it sounds pretty big, yeah.
はい。
Yeah.
ま、そんな感じですかね。
So that's pretty much it.
はい、ありがとーねーちゃん！
Okay, thank you, Nee-chan!
Wait, did you totally bribe the MC?
Okay.
Why'd you bribe the MC?
No way!
じゃあ、ヨピっていきますか？
So, shall we go with Yopi?
はい、ドッキンです！
Yes, it's 'dokkin'!
はい、ドッキン、ドッキン、ドッキン、ドッキン！
Yes, 'dokkin, dokkin, dokkin, dokkin'!
えじゃあ、カボ。
Um, then, Kabo.
I remember to mock Zeta about a part of her original song lyrics, it's 'babu-babu' but it's actually 'baku-baku-baku'...
I remember to mock Zeta about her original song lyrics, it's 'babu-babu' but it's actually 'baku-baku-baku'...
something like that.
うまむすめ、ドキドキドキ、ドキュン、ドキュン！
Umamusume, doki-doki-doki, dokyun, dokyun!
ドキュン戻る！
Back to dokyun!
はい、はい、はい、なるほど、確かに。
Right, right, right, I see, exactly.
じゃあ、ベーちゃん。
Now, Bae-chan.
いやもう、ドキドキをもっと強くして、もはや心臓発作！ドッドッドッドッドッ…
Well, make 'dokidoki' even stronger, almost like a heart attack! Thump-thump-thump...
はい。じゃあ、ラオラ。
Okay. Next, Raora.
えーと、バクンバクン！バクンバクン！バクンバクン！
Um, bakun-bakun! Bakun-bakun! Bakun-bakun!
I was lifting recently, so...
あ、でも結構みんな違うんだけど、
Ah, but everyone's answers are quite different,
じゃあ、正解、正解者は…これね、全員正解でいいかなと思います。
So, the correct answer, the winners... I think it's fine for everyone to be correct.
Everyone's right!
おお、みんな！結構いろんな表現があって、へえー。
Oh, everyone! There are quite a few various expressions, huh.
まあ、ドキッとか、ドックン、ドックンとか、ドキドキ、ドキドキとか、ドッキン、ドッキン、とか、あとドッドッドッも強そう。
Well, like 'doki', 'dokkun dokkun', 'dokidoki', 'dokkin dokkin', and 'thump-thump-thump' sounds strong too.
死んでるよ！死にそう、死にそう。緊張してる時とかにドッドッドッて、よーくさ、おしおきね。
You're dying! When you're nervous, like 'thump-thump-thump', you know...
はい、というわけで全員正解！素晴らしい！やったー！
Right, so everyone is correct! Wonderful! Yay!
じゃあちょっと、今度は上図…上上図？
Now then, next is... skilled...?
今度は、今からとあるサウンドを聞いてもらいます。
Next, you'll listen to a certain sound.
チャンネルにね、ボイスを貼りますので聞く。
I'll post a voice clip in the channel, so listen to it.
なんと言っているんだろうかと、いう問題でございますね。
The question is, what are they saying?
何と言っているか？
What are they saying?
今がセミの鳴き声を送ります。
Now I'm sending a cicada's cry.
なんと言っているでしょうか、セミは。
What is the cicada saying in the voice clip?
じゃあ、リスナーさんにも聞かせます。こちらです。
Now, we'll let the listeners hear it too. Here it is.
はい、これは何と…なるほど、なるほど。
Right, what is this... I see, I see.
みーー
Mii--
日本人だったらね、絶対わかるね。
If you're Japanese, you'd definitely get it.
How do you pronounce it? Cicada? Enchilada!
これは何と言うか、Cicada? Cicada!
What does it look like? Cicada? Cicada!
Is that big wings?
私聞いたことないかも
I might've never heard it before.
聞いたことある！時間に入り…
I've heard it all the time! Inside…
セミ？
A cicada?
え、聞いたことある。どこ？
Eh, I've heard it everywhere. Where?
これ分かった！JPやね。
I got this! It's JP.
さすがに…セミ？
As expected… a cicada?
本物の…
Real…
え、セミ聞いたことないんです。え、いないの？
Eh, I've never heard a cicada. Eh, aren't there any?
いや、いるとは思うけど、声は聞こえるけど、姿がどこにいるのかわかんない。
Well, I think they're there, I can hear their voices, but I don't know where they are.
そうなんだ。え、子供の頃蝉取りとかしないの？
Is that so? Eh, when you were a kid, did you catch cicadas?
ない。
No.
あれは多分インドネシアのなんか日本文化的な…
That's probably an Indonesian Japanese cultural thing…
へえ、そうなんだ。
Oh, is that so?
ないない。
Nope, nope.
じゃあ蝉の種類とか言われたままわかんないのか。
Then you wouldn't know the types of cicadas even if you were told.
わかんない。全員蝉だもん。
I don't know. They're all cicadas.
全員蝉だもん！ええー！
They're all cicadas! Whoa!
そうなんだ。
I see.
Anyone of you guys caught cicadas before? Sister? Sister? Sister? Ever caught one before?
No. No.
カカオは？ I got one in my balcony.
Kaka? I got one in my balcony.
え？
Eh?
バルコニー？
Your balcony?
Yeah, it was huge! It was like super big.
It was super loud.
バルコニーに…ベランダにいた？
In the balcony… was it on the veranda?
そんなに大きいの？蝉って。
Are cicadas really that big?
蝉、結構デカイよ。よくいるよ、そのへんで死んでるやつとか。
Cicadas are pretty big. You often see dead ones around.
まじ？ビッグバッグ。ここは大丈夫かな？
Really? Big bug. Is this place safe?
大丈夫じゃない！何回も聞いていいよ。大丈夫じゃない？何回も。
It's not safe! You can listen as many times as you want. Is it not safe? Every time.
大丈夫じゃない。
It's not safe.
Can I have hints? Hints on the game!
なんかあの「シャー、シャー、シャー」って言ってるのは無視していい。
You can ignore the ones going 'sha, sha, sha'.
その大きい、低めの音のセミさんはなんて言ってるからね。
Listen to what the big, lower-pitched cicada is saying.
Focus on the lowest sounding notes, ignore the sha-sha-sha in the background.
困ってるね。
You're in trouble, huh?
オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay.
じゃあ、行きましょう。よぴぴから。
Then let's go, starting with Yopipi.
はい。みーみーってな、みーみーはい、みーみーね、オッケー。
Yes. Mi-mi, mi-mi, yes, mi-mi, okay.
じい！じい！かわいい。じい！じいじいじい！じいじい、かわいい！かわいい！
Jii! Jii! Cute. Jii! Jiji-jiji! Jiji, cute! Cute!
じゃあじじ。じじは、じじじじ！じじじじ！じじじの声！じじじの声！おー。
Then Jiji. Jiji is, jiji-jiji! Jiji-jiji! Jiji's voice! Jiji's voice! Oh.
じゃあ、続いてべちゃ。うぃー！うぃー！うぃー！オッケーオッケー。
Then, next is Becha. Whee! Whee! Whee! Okay, okay.
じゃあ、ラストララ。え、クリックリックリ！かわいい。クリックリックリ！オッケーオッケー。
Then, last is Lala. Eh, click-click-click! Cute. Click-click-click! Okay, okay.
じゃあ正解行きましょう。正解は…はい！みーみみみみみで！
Now let's go with the correct answer. The correct answer is… Yes! Mi-mi-mi-mi-mi!
よぴぴ正解です！やったー！
Yopipi is correct! Yay!
It sounds like 'min' and 'mi'!
Japanese… can't you hear 'm' sound? There's no 'm' sound.
この蝉の名前がそもそもミンミンゼミという名前の蝉でね。
The name of this cicada is originally called the Minmin-zemi cicada.
ミンミンゼミって日本人には聞こえてますね。
It sounds like 'minmin-zemi' to Japanese people.
じゃあ、続いてネクストセミいきますよ。
Now, let's go to the next cicada.
ネクストセミ？え、どんな感じ？あれ？
Next cicada? Eh, what's it like? Huh?
ワンモアセミいきます。ワンモアセミ、セミ2、こちらです。じゃあ皆さんにも聞かせます。
Let's do one more cicada. One more cicada, Cicada 2, here it is. Then let's let everyone listen.
セミ2。なんか変だな？
Cicada 2. Something's weird, huh?
なんか変だぞ！待って待って、めっちゃうるさい！
Something's weird! Wait, wait, it's super loud!
はいはい、めっちゃ聞こえますね。多分日本人にはめちゃめちゃ聞こえる。
Yes, yes, we can hear it super well. Probably Japanese people can hear it extremely well.
Where's this sound from? I don't know.
What the heck? Hehe, ho-he-ha!
蝉バージョン2ですよ。
It's cicada version 2.
Mating Call.
わかるかな？
Do you know?
蝉2ね。
Cicada 2, right.
蝉2？すげえ。
Cicada 2? Amazing.
ヒントお願いします。
Please give us a hint.
ヒント？
A hint?
皆さん、あの
Everyone, um...
タタタタタ、タタタタタって言うのが鳴き声
the "ta-ta-ta-ta-ta, ta-ta-ta-ta-ta" call
が、日本人には
Well, for Japanese people,
タタタタタって、だから、まあ5文字くらいかな？
"ta-ta-ta-ta-ta"—so, about 5 characters, right?
みたいな感じのサウンド、が、そのパターン
like that kind of sound—that pattern.
ヒント、難しいね、これは。えー、ヒントとしてはむずいな。
Hints are hard, this one. Um, as a hint, it's pretty tough.
ちょ、タタタタタもオノマトペだったと言われたら、もうごめんなさい、それは
Wait, if you tell me "ta-ta-ta-ta-ta" was also an onomatopoeia, I'm sorry, that...
ええ？むずい
Huh? That's hard.
タタタタタタタタタタしかもうしてない
It's literally just "ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta."
7文字？
7 characters?
7文字...ずるい
7 characters... that's cheating.
まあ、伸ばし棒が入ります、あと、最後のほうに。
Well, there's a prolonged sound mark near the end.
え？伸ばして...
Eh? Stretching...
伸ばすと7文字ですね。
Stretching it makes it 7 characters.
難しいねえ。このリズム、次回は分かるんだけど、どう変えていけばいいのか分かんない、落ち着く。
It's hard. This rhythm—next time I'll get it, but I don't know how to change it so it's calming.
この声を聴くと落ち着きますよ、夏だなあって。
Listening to this voice calms you down, makes you feel like "Ah, it's summer."
え？
Eh?
むずくね？
Isn't that hard?
じゃあ行きましょうか。
Well then, shall we go?
よぴぴから。
Starting with Yopipi.
いや、くくくくくじゃないですか？セミバージョン2。
Wait, isn't it "ku-ku-ku-ku-ku"? Cicada Version 2.
セミバージョン2？くくくくく！くくく！ぐっぐ！
Cicada Version 2? "Ku-ku-ku-ku-ku! Ku-ku-ku! Gu-gu!"
ええと、その、さっきのは「みんみん」でしょ？うん、あーはん。で、えー、聞いた感じこれは「みんみん」より多くて、だから「めー、めー、めー、めー」...あ、「めぐめぐめぐめぐ」...いや、「めんめん、めんめん、めんめん」みたいな...
Um, so the previous one was "ming-ming," right? And I feel like this is more than "ming-ming," so it's like "mang-mang, mang-mang, mang-mang"...
そもそもなんで「メイティングコール」って書いたの？
First of all, why did you write "Mating Call"?
ええと、QIの鳴き声「めんめん」です。
Um, QI's call is "men-men."
ああ、でもQIの鳴き声なんだよね、実際。
Ah, but it actually is QI's call.
え、そうなの？
Eh, really?
そう！イエス！だからそこへ、そう、it is a Mating Call! It is a Mating Call! Oh my god!
Yes! Yes! That's why—see, it is a Mating Call! It is a Mating Call! Oh my god!
セミのオスが、あの、メス来いやって言っている時の声だから、そこは正しい、QIね。
Because that's the sound a male cicada makes when saying "Hey females, come here," so that part is correct, QI.
あ、でも、でも「めんめん」で正しいかどうかね。
Ah, but whether "men-men" is correct or not.
あ、そう、「めんめん」ね。
Ah, right, "men-men," huh?
オーケー？
Okay?
あい、オッケーって言って、ジジ。
I, okay, and then Gigi.
じじじじじじじじ...じじじ、オッケー。
Ji-ji-ji-ji-ji-ji... Ji-ji-ji, okay.
べちゃ？なんか、ぽくぽくぴかぽくぽくぴか...ポケモンみたいな音だけど、ポケモン、ポケモンみたい。オッケー。
Becha? Like, "poku-poku-pika-poku-poku-pika"—sounds like Pokémon, Pokémon-like. Okay.
じゃあ、ラオラ。いまゆぴにゅう、it's a cricket.
Well then, Raora. Yopipi said, "It's a cricket."
And a cricket sounds like プリイプリイ...あ、プリイプリイ、かわいい。
And a cricket sounds like prii-prii-prii-prii... Ah, prii-prii, cute.
プリンプリンね、プリンプリン。オーケーオーケー、プレイキュー。
Pudding pudding, right? Pudding pudding. Okay, okay, play cricket.
じゃあ、行きます。こちらの鳴き声は、「ツクツクボウシ」でございます。
Well then, here we go. This cicada call is... "Tsukutsukuboushi"!
えー！？
Eh?!
な、な、な、なんで？なんで？なんで？なんで？
Wh-wh-wh-why? Why? Why? Why?
ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシツクツクボウシ！
Tsukutsukuboushi! Tsukutsukuboushi! Tsukutsukuboushi!
So I should do this if I want to mating call someone?
ノットジジ、ノットジジ、キュイの鳴き声、ノットジジ！ツクツクボウシツクツクボウシ！
Not gigi, not gigi, Qyi's call, not gigi! Tsukutsukuboushi!
ツクツクボウシツクツクボウシ！やばい、やばい、やばい、やばいシャ、プリーズ！
Tsukutsukuboushi! Oh no, oh no, oh no, sha, please!
わかんなくなっちゃった！
I got all confused!
これは「ツクツクボウシ」っていうセミの鳴き声ですね、いまのは。
This is the cicada call called "Tsukutsukuboushi," the one just now.
そう、種類も「ツクツクボウシ」っていう名前のセミ。
Yes, the species is also a cicada named "Tsukutsukuboushi."
ちなみに他にも、さっきのがミンミンゼミだったでしょ？アブラゼミっていうのが、あの、ジジがさっき言ってた「じじじじじじじじ」って鳴くのがアブラゼミ。
By the way, besides that, the previous one was the Minmin cicada, right? The "Aburazemi" is the one—um, what Gigi was saying earlier—that's the Aburazemi.
あ、油ゼミ？
Ah, abrasemi?
はい。
Yes.
日本人だったらセミの声を聞くだけで、何のセミかわかります。
If you're Japanese, just by hearing a cicada's call, you know what kind of cicada it is.
えー！
Whoa!
They can differentiate what kind of cicada it is depending on what it sounds like.
There's different enchiladas.
Enchilada? Yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas, Gigi.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says "ji ji"?
じじじじ。
Ji-ji-ji-ji.
Yes.
そのあつ、え？3種類って何の名前だっけ？
Wait, what were the names of those three types?
ええと、3種類の、ジジジジは油ゼミですね。
Um, of the three types, "ji-ji-ji-ji" is the abrasemi.
油ゼミ。はい。油ゼミ。油ゼミ。 Yes. 油ゼミ。
Abrasemi. Yes. Abrasemi. Abrasemi. Yes. Abrasemi.
A large brown cicada goes... なるほど。
A large brown cicada goes... I see.
なるほどね。なるほどね。じゃあ、次たラスト問題。
I see. I see. Okay, next is the final question.
あ、ラスト！あ、ラス！これはめちゃ、ちょっとジャパニーズすぎる、難しいと思うんですけど、え、これ解けたらもう、いついつ日本に来ても戦えます。
Ah, the last one! Ah, last! This is super... a bit too Japanese, I think it's difficult, but hey, if you solve this, you can fight whenever you come to Japan.
えっ、誰？
Huh, who?
カイナ？
Kaina?
ええ、日本には独特な、これにしか使えないオノマトペがあります。
Uh, Japan has a unique onomatopoeia used only for this.
おお、桃が川から流れてくるオノマトペは何でしょう？
Oh, what is the onomatopoeia for a peach floating down a river?
What is the onomatopoeia for when a peach comes flowing down the river?
スライド。
Slide.
桃太郎を呼んでないんだったら、これ桃太郎呼んでないんだったらできないじゃないですか、これ桃太郎。
If you don't call Momotaro, if you don't call Momotaro, you can't do this, right, Momotaro?
これ分かったら、もう日本に来ていただいていつでも。
If you figure this out, please come to Japan anytime.
What is the sound that a peach makes when it flows down the river? It's a very, very specific onomatopoeia. I'm guessing if you know the story of...
桃太郎？いや、違う。日本のフォロワー？
Momotaro? No, wait. Japanese folklore?
Yeah, you know the peach boy, the Momotaro, peach boy. Yes. Yeah, it's very specific. I... wait, what could it... what could it be?
桃にしか使えないですね。リンゴとかが代わり流れてても使えない。
It's only used for peaches. Even if an apple or something floated by instead, you wouldn't use it.
I only use it for peaches. It's only peaches. No, I'm sure this is going to be really weird.
桃太郎呼んでないたらわかんないやつ。
If you haven't read Momotaro, you wouldn't get it.
いや、桃太郎1回読んだんだよね。
Well, I read Momotaro once.
お、じゃあわかるじゃん。
Oh, then you know.
Maybe I know that, don't play. Oh, cuz I've watched...
If you read the actual book, it it's written in the actual book, like in Japanese. So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
If you read the actual book, it's written in the actual book, like in Japanese. So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
こんなことあんの！？
Is that even a thing?!
なんか確か前にあの雑談配信でこのことちょっと語った気がする。
I feel like I talked about this on a chatting stream before.
あ、そうなんだ！
Oh, really!
そう、なんでこうなんだって言われたらわかんないけど。
Yeah, if you ask me why it became like this, I don't know.
すごいね、でも話すんだ。
That's amazing, but you talk about it.
昔話ね。
Folktales, huh.
なんだっけ。
What was it again?
これはね、ま、多分知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど。
This one, if you don't know it, you really won't be able to guess it.
日本人だったら、あのちっちゃい子からおじちゃんおばあちゃんまでみんなわかるからね。
If you're Japanese, everyone from little kids to old folks knows it.
ももの川流れてる音なんだって。
It's the sound of a peach flowing down a river, you know.
はい、じゃあ行きましょうか。最終問題、じゃあよぴぴどうでしょう？
Okay, shall we go? Final question, Yopipi, what do you think?
はい、どんぶらこです。
Yes, it's "donburako."
はい、どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ。
Yes, donburako, donburako.
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃあこぼちゃん。
Next, Kobo-chan.
お尻？もんごもんご。もんごもんご。もんごもんご。
Butt, mongo-mongo. Mongo-mongo. Mongo-mongo.
お尻みたい。流れでるの。あ、お尻みたいね。
It looks like an ass flowing by. Ah, like an ass.
Um, if I saw a huge peach floating in the water, and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and it was, you know, like a peach, I would go, "Ah, what? Dekai!" Like, "Meccha-meccha juicy, dekai!" Juicy! Dekai!
Um, if I saw a huge peach floating in the water, and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and it was, you know, like a peach, I would go, "Ah, what? Huge!" Like, "Super super juicy, huge!" Juicy! Huge!
お尻デカイ！お尻デカイ！
Big ass! Big ass!
じゃあべちゃん。
Then, Bae-chan.
なんか、どんぴしゃ！
Like, "donpisha!"
という、どんぴしゃ！水のね、水の音ね、どんぴしゃ！はい、どんぴしゃ！
That's right, "donpisha!" The sound of water, "donpisha!" Yes, "donpisha!"
うーん、maybe it's puka-puka. あ、puka-puka! Puka-puka, puka-puka, kawaii, puka-puka, mimi.
Hmm, maybe it's puka-puka. Ah, puka-puka! Puka-puka, puka-puka, kawaii, puka-puka, mimi.
オッケー。じゃあ正解行きましょう。
Okay, let's go to the correct answer.
どんぶらこ どんぶらこですね
Donburako, donburako, right?
なぜで なぜかは そうやって本に書いてあるからね
Why? Why, because that's how it's written in the book.
理由は ない
There's no reason.
え ちなみに 理由はない ない ない ないよ
Wait, by the way, is there a reason? There isn't, there isn't.
で あれだね プカプカは あの 浮いてる もの 水に浮いててたらプカプカで合ってる
And, puka puka is when things are floating in water, that's right.
そう で 桃が川から流れてくるときはどんぶらこ ですね
Right, but when a peach floats down a river, it's donburako.
あ りんごだったら りんごだったらプカプカ？
Ah, what about an apple? If it's an apple, puka puka?
ということでね え 皆さん
So, everyone...
ワイジャパン！
Why Japan?!
オノマトペ！
Onomatopoeia!
で ちなみに オノマトペではないんですけど 今日みんなにじゃあ 覚えてってほしい言葉があります
By the way, it's not onomatopoeia, but there's a word I want everyone to learn today.
全然わからないっていうのを 日本語ではちんぷんかんぷんと言いますね
When you completely don't understand something, in Japanese it's called chinpunkampun.
あー！ ちんぷんかんぷん！ かわいい！ ちんぷんかんぷん！ ぷん！ ちんぷんかんぷん！
Ah! Chinpunkampun! Cute! Chinpunkampun! Pun! Chinpunkampun!
ジャパン ホワイ？！ これは全然わからない
Japan, why?! This is completely incomprehensible.
ちんぷんかんぷん！オノマトペ！
Chinpunkampun! Onomatopoeia!
ちんぷんかんぷん 難しい言葉ですよ
Chinpunkampun is a difficult word.
なんか怖いな ちんぷんかんぷんの っていうオノマトペをね 全部 覚えられない時だ
It's kind of scary, when you can't remember all the onomatopoeia like chinpunkampun...
覚えて ちんぷんかんぷん 漢字もあるからね ちんぷんかんぷんって
Remember, chinpunkampun. There are kanji for chinpunkampun too.
え 漢字も？ そう 漢字もあるの カタカナじゃない
Eh, kanji too? Yes, there are kanji. It's not just katakana.
カタカナね ゆったりひらがなでいうことが多いけど ちゃんとね 漢字がある
Katakana, it's often said loosely in hiragana, but there are proper kanji.
漢字が？ そう 漢字があるの
Kanji? Yes, there are kanji.
コメントでね書いてくれてるけど
People are writing it in the comments.
なにこれ それがちんぷんかんぷんですね
What is this? That is chinpunkampun.
珍しい コーナー何？ 漢字の おにゃらおにゃらのオープン？ ちんぷんかんぷんですね
Unusual, what corner? Kanji's, onyaraponyara open? It's chinpunkampun.
でもめちゃくちゃかわいいから もし日本語わかんなくなったら あ 日本語ちんぷんかんぷんですって言ったら もうオッケー 全て解決
But it's super cute, so if you don't understand Japanese anymore, just say "Ah, my Japanese is chinpunkampun," and it's all good. Everything solved.
オッケー オッケーだった オッケー ということで
Okay, okay then. Okay, so...
岡山県 ワンオノマトピアダ 岡ゆう先輩タップミーワンス
Okayama Prefecture One Onomatopoeia-ta, Okayama Yuu-senpai tapped me once?
岡ゆう先輩に教えてくれたオノマトペがあります
There's an onomatopoeia Okayama Yuu-senpai taught me.
何ですか？
What is it?
え え ブルンブルンです
Uh, uh, it's burun burun!
ブルンブルンは おっぱいを揺らすときの音
Burun burun is the sound when shaking boobs!
ボインボイン ボインボイン ボインボイン ブルンブルン オッケー 合ってる 両方おっぱい
Boin boin, boin boin, boin boin, burun burun, okay, both are correct for boobs.
で もっと大きな おっぱいだと バインバインになります
And for even bigger boobs, it becomes bain bain.
バインバイン！ もっと大きな おっぱいだと バインバイン
Bain bain! For even bigger boobs, bain bain.
それ以上大きなブルはないですか？ それ以上大きいのはないね
Are there no bigger burus than that? There aren't any bigger ones.
多分バインバインが一番大きい
Probably bain bain is the biggest.
今日の優勝者 一応発表しますか。
Shall we announce today's winner?
今日はですね、よぴぴが優勝でございます。
Today, Yopipi is our winner!
もうほぼ… あ、やった！
Almost... Ah, yay!
すごーい！半分以上正解して
Amazing! She got over half of them right,
すごい！天才だ、さすがでございます。
incredible! A true genius, as expected.
いやいや…日本語上手！でもね、
No, no... her Japanese is so good! But you know,
他のメンバーも、半分は正解してますから素晴らしいでございます。
the other members also got half right, so they're wonderful too!
おー、やったー！
Oh, yay!
ということで、みなさん本日もありがとうございました。
And with that, everyone, thank you very much for today as well.
チャンネル登録もね、あ、チャンネル登録ありがとうございます！
And for subscribing to the channel too—ah, thank you for subscribing! Thank you!
チャンネル登録の方も、え、ポチッとおねがいしますね。
Please also make sure to click and subscribe to the channel.
はい、ポチ、お願いします！
Yes, please click it!
じゃ、最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ。
Now, we'll wrap things up with a bye-bye.
せーの、バイバーイ！
Ready, set, bye-bye!
ちゅーぶかんぽん、ちゅーぶかんぽん…
Chubukampon, chubukampon...